A Guide to the Receipts and Disbursements Journals of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, 1778-1797
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Receipts and Disbursements Journals of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, 1778-1797
The Library of Virginia
APA 45
21 volumes
Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available. Received circa 1913.
Alternate Form of Material
Microfilm copy available (Miscellaneous Reel 6251-6262)
Funding for the preservation microfilming of these records was made possible through the sponsorship of the Virginia State Society, National Society Daughters of the American Revolution (NSDAR).
Biographical Information
Although the colonial government had appointed auditors general from time to time, the office was not established on a permanent basis until after independence was declared. At its first session, which convened on 7 October 1776, the General Assembly passed an act creating a board of three auditors to examine and settle claims concerning receipts and expenditures for military purposes. The confusing financial situation of the state, however, resulted in a series of acts being passed over the next fifteen years elaborating and refining the duties of the auditors. Finally, at its session begun in November 1791, the General Assembly passed an act that combined the duties of the board of auditors and the solicitor general, whose office had been created in 1785 to settle the accounts of the state with the United States, and assigned them to a single auditor of public accounts effective 1 January 1792. The auditor soon became the most powerful fiscal officer in the state. All receipts and disbursements were made only upon his warrant to the treasurer, and his books were the standard against which those of the treasurer were checked.
The first changes were made as the accounts of the revolutionary era were settled. As the state moved into a period of steady financial and governmental growth in the nineteenth century, the number of accounts and funds maintained by the auditor became excessive. Thus, on 24 February 1823 the General Assembly passed an act creating the office of the second auditor to ease the auditor’s burden. Although the second auditor handled several large special funds, the auditor continued to be responsible for most of the accounts concerning the daily operation of state government.
During the Civil War both the state government and the pro-Union Restored Government of Virginia, which was based first in Wheeling and then in Alexandria, had auditors of public accounts. After the war, near the end of Reconstruction, the military authorities appointed Major Thaddeus H. Stanton, of the United States Army, as auditor of public accounts. Stanton was paid by the state during his service from 3 April 1869 to 12 February 1870, although he remained an army officer. The position was returned to civilian control on 12 February 1870 with the election of William F. Taylor as auditor by the General Assembly.
Following the Civil War the complexities of an increasingly sophisticated financial world threatened to overwhelm the state fiscal offices, which had changed their practices but little since the end of the eighteenth century. Inadequate bookkeeping procedures and embezzlements of state funds resulted in a public demand for corrective action. It was not until a state government reorganization act was passed by the General Assembly on 18 April 1927, however, that the demand was satisfied. Effective 1 March 1928 the office of auditor of public accounts and second auditor were abolished and replaced by the office of comptroller--head of the Department of Accounts--to monitor the receipt and disbursement of state funds, and a new office of auditor of public accounts, under the General Assembly, to audit state and local government agencies.
Scope and Content
These volumes are comprised of daily entries of revenues and expenditures, many of which document payments for Revolutionary War service and public service contributions. Individual entries include titles of funds or accounts, names of payers or payees, dates paid in or out, and amounts, and include payments for military service in the militia and Continental Line and for other military services rendered, relief payments to disabled soldiers and widows, interest paid on military certificates, and reimbursement for impressed property, as well as payments to individuals for civil services and to members of the General Assembly.
Volumes cover the period from 14 December 1778 to 6 July 1797. Beginning 1 January 1791 separate series were created for receipts and disbursements (entries 40 and 42). Receipts were recorded occasionally in this series, however, until 6 July 1797.
Arrangement
These volumes are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I. Receipts and Disbursements Journals, 1778-1797.
  - Journal, 1778 December 14-1779 September 25 (Miscellaneous Reel 6251).
  - Journal, 1779 September 27-1780 May 10 (Miscellaneous Reel 6251).
  - Journal, 1780 May 11-1781 January 3 (Miscellaneous Reel 6251).
  - Journal, 1781 January 17-1783 December 24 (Miscellaneous Reel 6252).
  - Journal, 1782 January 5-December 21 (Miscellaneous Reel 6253).
  - Journal, 1782 December 21-1783 April 25 (Miscellaneous Reel 6253).
  - Journal, 1783 April 25-October 29 (Miscellaneous Reel 6254).
  - Journal, 1783 October 30-1784 May 22 (Miscellaneous Reel 6255).
  - Journal, 1784 May 24-August 9(Miscellaneous Reel 6256).
  - Journal, 1784 August 9-December 14 (Miscellaneous Reel 6256).
  - Journal, 1784 December 15-31 (Miscellaneous Reel 6256).
  - Journal, 1786 January 2-May 31 (Miscellaneous Reel 6257).
  - Journal, 1786 June 1-December 30 (Miscellaneous Reel 6257).
  - Journal, 1787 March 3-August 31 (Miscellaneous Reel 6258).
  - Journal, 1787 September 5-1788 May 7 (Miscellaneous Reel 6259).
  - Journal, 1788 May 8-August 30 (Miscellaneous Reel 6259).
  - Journal, 1788 September 1-1789 March 19 (Miscellaneous Reel 6260).
  - Journal, 1789 March 20-August 31 (Miscellaneous Reel 6260).
  - Journal, 1789 September 1-1790 April 22 (Miscellaneous Reel 6261).
  - Journal, 1790 April 23-November 18 (Miscellaneous Reel 6261).
  - Journal, 1790 November 19-1797 September 30 (Miscellaneous Reel 6262).